<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
	<idinfo>
		<citation>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>Brown, P. J.</origin>
				<origin>Grauch, V. J.</origin>
				<pubdate>2019</pubdate>
				<title>High Resolution Aeromagnetic Survey, Villa Grove, Colorado, USA 2012</title>
				<geoform>Binary Files and ASCII text</geoform>
				<pubinfo>
					<pubplace>Denver, CO</pubplace>
					<publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
				</pubinfo>
				<othercit>Additional information about Originators: Brown, P.J., http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2415-7462; Grauch, V. J., https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0761-3489</othercit>
				<onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F7416V52</onlink>
			</citeinfo>
		</citation>
		<descript>
			<abstract>This data release includes the airborne magnetic survey data collected from the Manchester region of Iowa. The Mineral Resources Program of the U.S. Geological Survey is tasked with understanding the nation's mineral resources. Precambrian rocks concealed under Paleozoic sedimentary rocks in northeast Iowa are poorly mapped and understood. Detailed high-resolution airborne magnetic surveys, ground gravity surveys, and limited borehole data are being used to better understand the lithology and structure of concealed Precambrian rocks. The primary goal of the airborne magnetic survey is to map lateral variations of magnetization that are related to differences in rock type.</abstract>
			<purpose>The purpose of this data release is to provide the data to the public. Detailed high-resolution airborne magnetic surveys, ground gravity surveys, and limited borehole data are being used to better understand the lithology and structure of concealed Precambrian rocks. The primary goal of the airborne magnetic survey is to map lateral variations of magnetization that are related to differences in rock type.</purpose>
			<supplinf>This metadata describes six files
 {fileListing}
			This data release contains grid files in ASCII Text Grid Exchange Format (gxf). GXF (Grid eXchange File) is a standard ASCII file format for exchanging gridded data among different software systems.
			More information about the Geosoft GXF file visit http://www.geosoft.com/resources/goto/GXF-Grid-eXchange-File. The data were originally relased from the contractor in Geosoft Oasis montaj (https://www.geosoft.com/products/oasis-montaj) Geosoft Data Base (GDB) and Geosoft Grid (GRD) formats.  A free viewer tool can be downladed from Geosoft to read these formats at the following URL, https://www.geosoft.com/products/geosoft-viewer</supplinf>
		</descript>
		<timeperd>
			<timeinfo>
				<rngdates>
					<begdate>20111023</begdate>
					<enddate>20111126</enddate>
				</rngdates>
			</timeinfo>
			<current>Ground Condition</current>
		</timeperd>
		<status>
			<progress>Complete</progress>
			<update>None Planned</update>
		</status>
		<spdom>
			<bounding>
				<westbc>-106.22628</westbc>
				<eastbc>-105.564178</eastbc>
				<northbc>38.616119</northbc>
				<southbc>37.803234</southbc>
			</bounding>
		</spdom>
		<keywords>
			<theme>
				<themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
				<themekey>geophysics</themekey>
				<themekey>magnetic surveying</themekey>
				<themekey>aeromagnetic surveying</themekey>
				<themekey>magnetic field (earth)</themekey>
				<themekey>geospatial datasets</themekey>
			</theme>
			<theme>
				<themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
				<themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
			</theme>
			<theme>
				<themekt>none</themekt>
				<themekey>aeromag</themekey>
				<themekey>aeromagnetic</themekey>
				<themekey>airborne magnetic survey</themekey>
				<themekey>MRP</themekey>
				<themekey>Minerals Resources Program</themekey>
				<themekey>GGGSC</themekey>
				<themekey>Geology, Geophysics, and Geochemistry Science Center</themekey>
			</theme>
			<place>
				<placekt>USGS Geographic Names Information System (GNIS)</placekt>
				<placekey>Colorado</placekey>
				<placekey>City of Salida</placekey>
				<placekey>San Luis Creek</placekey>
				<placekey>Chaffee County</placekey>
				<placekey>Saguache County</placekey>
				<placekey>Fremont County</placekey>
			</place>
		</keywords>
		<accconst>None. Please see ‘Distribution Info’ for details.</accconst>
		<useconst>There is no guarantee concerning the accuracy of the data. Any user who modifies the data is obligated to describe the types of modifications they perform. Data have been checked to ensure the accuracy. If any errors are detected, please notify the originating office. The U.S. Geological Survey strongly recommends that careful attention be paid to the metadata file associated with these data. Acknowledgment of the U.S. Geological Survey would be appreciated in products derived from these data. User specifically agrees not to misrepresent the data, nor to imply that changes made were approved or endorsed by the U.S. Geological Survey. Please refer to http://www.usgs.gov/privacy.html for the USGS disclaimer.</useconst>
		<ptcontac>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntorgp>
					<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Crustal Geophysics and Geochemistry Science Center</cntorg>
					<cntper>Grauch, V. J.</cntper>
				</cntorgp>
				<cntpos>Research Geophysicist</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
					<address>POB 25046 DFC, MS 964</address>
					<city>Denver</city>
					<state>Colorado</state>
					<postal>80225</postal>
					<country>USA</country>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>303-236-1425</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>tien@usgs.gov</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</ptcontac>
		<datacred>USGS Mineral Resource Program provided the funding.  These data were acquired by EON Geosciences Inc. (EON) for the U.S. Geological Survey.</datacred>
		<native>MS Windows Geosoft Oasis montaj, http://www.geosoft.com/products/oasis-montaj/overview.</native>
	</idinfo>
	<dataqual>
		<attracc>
			<attraccr>The data have been processed using various formulas and methods that are not usually documented but that represent industry standard practices for airborne data reduction.  For example, position is listed as latitude and longitude, but these values were derived from the raw navigation data depending on the system used. (see notes under horizontal accuracy). Line numbers were added to records, and unusable data at flight-line ends were discarded (as aircraft slowed and turned around). Separate recordings were correlated by time and assigned to the correct location.
			The exact accuracies of these processing steps may not be known. They are discussed in the sections on attribute or positional accuracies. </attraccr>
		</attracc>
		<logic>The data on the original map were collected by a single contractor or group who were responsible for collecting and processing the data. The data from this survey were collected using the same instruments (magnetometers, altimeters, navigational systems) throughout the survey and were collected in a normal length of time with no long delays between survey beginning and end. Survey layout specified the conditions and specifications under which these data were collected. Standard industry practices of the time were followed in data collection and processing.</logic>
		<complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
		<posacc>
			<horizpa>
				<horizpar>Recorded airborne raw GPS data were used for DGPS post-processing, using the NovAtel Waypoint software. Waypoint PP-DGPS computations were made either in differential mode, using raw data of the  GPS base station, or in precise point positioning (PPP) mode, using CSRS precise clocks and ephemeris data available at the Natural Resource Canada web site. Base station positioning was performed in PPP mode. Mean sea level (MSL) elevations were referenced to the EGM-96-World ellipsoidal-to-orthometric model. Daily and final PP-DGPS quality control, based on the analysis of velocity profiles and on comparison of PP-DGPS, RT-DGPS, and barometric altitudes, ascertained that RT-DGPS precision remained suitable for navigation (less than 5 m) and that Waypoint post-processing improved positioning precision to the order of 1m.</horizpar>
			</horizpa>
			<vertacc>
				<vertaccr>Recorded airborne raw GPS data were used for DGPS post-processing, using the NovAtel Waypoint software. Waypoint PP-DGPS computations were made either in differential mode, using raw data of the  GPS base station, or in precise point positioning (PPP) mode, using CSRS precise clocks and ephemeris data available at the Natural Resource Canada web site. Base station positioning was performed in PPP mode. Mean sea level (MSL) elevations were referenced to the EGM-96-World ellipsoidal-to-orthometric model. Daily and final PP-DGPS quality control, based on the analysis of velocity profiles and on comparison of PP-DGPS, RT-DGPS, and barometric altitudes, ascertained that RT-DGPS precision remained suitable for navigation (less than 5 m) and that Waypoint post-processing improved positioning precision to the order of 1m.</vertaccr>
			</vertacc>
		</posacc>
		<lineage>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>EON Geosciences Inc.</origin>
						<pubdate>2015</pubdate>
						<title>United States Geological Survey (USGS), HIGH RESOLUTION AEROMAGNETIC SURVEY, Villa Grove, Colorado, FINAL SURVEY REPORT</title>
						<geoform>Geosoft database, Grids, and PDF</geoform>
						<pubinfo>
							<pubplace>Montreal, Quebec, Canada</pubplace>
							<publish>EON Geosciences Inc.</publish>
						</pubinfo>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<typesrc>geophysical database</typesrc>
				<srctime>
					<timeinfo>
						<sngdate>
							<caldate>2011</caldate>
						</sngdate>
					</timeinfo>
					<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
				</srctime>
				<srccitea>mag_survey</srccitea>
				<srccontr>Magnetic total-field survey data</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Daily quality control, initial processing and archiving of the data were done on-site at the base of operations in Salida, CO.</procdesc>
				<procdate>20120203</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>The final data processing, map generation and report writing were undertaken at the offices of EON Geosciences Inc. (EON), Montreal, Quebec, Canada . Processing steps for the magnetic data involve several steps, which are outlined in the 11003_VillaGrove_Final_Survey_Report.pdf that is part of this data release.</procdesc>
				<procdate>20120131</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Final contractor data were exported from .GDF format to .CSV format to meet open data requirements.</procdesc>
				<procdate>20190524</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
		<procdesc>Final unprojected contractor data grids were projected to WGS84, UTM Zone 13 North as speculated given the statistics of the grids' horizontal extents.</procdesc>
				<procdate>20190530</procdate>
			</procstep>
		</lineage>
	</dataqual>
	<spdoinfo>
		<direct>Point</direct>
	</spdoinfo>
	<spref>
		<horizsys>
			<geograph>
				<latres>0.00001</latres>
				<longres>0.00001</longres>
				<geogunit>Decimal Degrees</geogunit>
			</geograph>
			<geodetic>
				<horizdn>WGS84</horizdn>
				<ellips>WGS84</ellips>
				<semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
				<denflat>298.25722</denflat>
			</geodetic>
		</horizsys>
	</spref>
	<eainfo>
		<detailed>
			<enttyp>
				<enttypl>HighResolutionAeromagneticSurveyVillaGroveColorado2012.csv</enttypl>
				<enttypd>ASCII Text CSV Table of Airborne Survey Results</enttypd>
				<enttypds>U.S. Geological Survey</enttypds>
			</enttyp>
 {csvAttributes}
		</detailed>
 {bFilesEntAttText}
 </eainfo>
	<distinfo>
		<distrib>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntorgp>
					<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, ScienceBase</cntorg>
					<cntper>U.S. Geological Survey, ScienceBase</cntper>
				</cntorgp>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
					<address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
					<city>Denver</city>
					<state>Colorado</state>
					<postal>80225</postal>
					<country>USA</country>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</distrib>
		<distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.</distliab>
	</distinfo>
	<metainfo>
		<metd>20190531</metd>
		<metc>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntper>Philip J. Brown</cntper>
					<cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>Geophysicist</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
					<address>POB 25046 DFC, MS 964</address>
					<city>Denver</city>
					<state>CO</state>
					<postal>80225</postal>
					<country>USA</country>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>(303) 236-1310</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>pbrown@usgs.gov</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</metc>
		<metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
		<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
	</metainfo>
</metadata>
